<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discourse of licenses to preach occasioned by a question propounded, viz., why many officers of the Church of England in the episcopal visitations urge the incumbents to take licenses to preach / replied to by Ja. Metford in a letter to the proposer ; published for the consideration of the clergy to whom it is of no small importance.</title>
            <author>Metford, James.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1698</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 92 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50759</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1937</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R27111</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09653441</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09653441</idno>
            <idno type="VID">43918</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A50759)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 43918)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1336:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discourse of licenses to preach occasioned by a question propounded, viz., why many officers of the Church of England in the episcopal visitations urge the incumbents to take licenses to preach / replied to by Ja. Metford in a letter to the proposer ; published for the consideration of the clergy to whom it is of no small importance.</title>
                  <author>Metford, James.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for H. Hindmarsh,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1698.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  History.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Clergy.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:43918:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:43918:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DISCOURSE OF Licenſes to Preach.</p>
            <p>OCCASIONED <hi>By a Queſtion Propounded,</hi> viz.</p>
            <p>Why many Officers of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> in the Epiſcopal Viſitations, urge the Incumbents, to take LICENSES to Preach.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Replyed to by</hi> Ja. Metford <hi>Rector of</hi> Baſingham, <hi>in the County of</hi> Lincoln: <hi>In a Letter to the Propoſer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Publiſhed for the Conſideration of the CLERGY, to whom it is of no ſmall Importance.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>H. Hindmarſh,</hi> at the <hi>Golden-Ball</hi> over againſt the <hi>Royal Exchange</hi> in <hi>Cornhil.</hi> 1698.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:43918:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:43918:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Righ Reverend Father in God, <hi>JAMES</hi> by Divine Providence Lord Biſhop of <hi>Lincoln.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WE can never be enough Thankful to his Sacred Majeſty, the great Patron of this Church; that He was pleaſed to honour Us, with a Biſhop, taken from among our Selves, to fill the Chair of this Ancient See of <hi>Lincoln:</hi> who is neither Ignorant of our Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, nor our Needs, nor unwilling to Hear and Reſolve our Doubts. This ſmall Diſſertation therefore, comes in all Humility, and with moſt profound Reſpect, to ſhew your Lordſhip, the Senſe of moſt of your Clergy, about an odd Cuſtom, introduced in theſe later Ages, of Oblig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Incumbents to take <hi>Licenſes to Preach.</hi> And that, even after they have received Ordination, and Inſtitution.</p>
            <p>We believe that your Lordſhip intends not to elumbate the Dignity of Preiſthood: nor to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulſe its Eſſential, (or at leaſt Integral) Parts,
<pb facs="tcp:43918:3"/>from each other. And accordingly that you will never permit, any Conſideration, to gain that Aſcendency in your Thoughts, as to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue a Cuſtom, utterly unknown to the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, and middle times; and unuſeful in theſe. And can furniſh Us with nothing but Scruples in our Selves, and Objections againſt us in our Adverſaries.</p>
            <p>We know that you have Kindneſs enough, to forgive the Weakneſs of Management; and Wiſdom enough to ſtrengthen its defects, where it needs; and therefore do humbly ſubmit the whole matter to your ſound Judgment: in full aſſurance, that you will add to the Bleſſing of our publick Peace, by giving us private ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, in withdrawing this Cuſtom, or at leaſt to Inſtruct us in the neceſſity of its Continuance, who have no other Deſign, but to be Dutiful, whatever is determined: and to be taught what we do not underſtand; which will be abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly obliging to All, but more eſpecially to</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My LORD,</salute> 
               <signed>Your Devoted Subject and most Humble Servant, <hi>J. M.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:43918:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A</hi> Diſcourſe of Licenſes to Preach.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE <hi>Quaere</hi> laſt Night Propounded: why Licenſes to Preach, are ſo frequently, and vehemently urged to to be taken, and Exhibited, by Incumbents; in our Epiſcopal Viſitations: being then Anſwered with ſome haeſitation, the help of a few hours Thoughts, gives me the advantage of ſetting this matter in a clearer Light before you. Which I think (for want of a better Method) may be done by elucidating theſe Seven enſuing Propoſitions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> That Ordination to Prieſthood, gives Authority to the Ordained to Preach.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> That the Church for 1400 years, never required Incumbents of Benefices, to take Licenſes to Preach.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> That the Church Canons enjoyned all Incumbents to Preach, under great Penalties.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> When Licenſes were firſt Introduced, they did not oblige Incumbents to take them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> If the Canons did ever oblige Incumbents to take Licenſes: It was upon an accidental Conſideration.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixthly,</hi> That Licenſes add, nor, diminiſh any thing, to or from the Title to any Benefice.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seventhly,</hi> That the forcing Incumbents to take Licenſes (ſince the firſt Accidental Occaſion) was of no Benefit to the Church, but to gain Fees.</p>
            <p>Theſe Propoſitions made good, will infer the Truth of my Sudden Anſwer. That theſe Licenſes are preſſed upon Incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bents upon very mean Conſiderations. I ſhall therefore apply my ſelf to clear them in Order.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:43918:4"/>
            <p n="1">I. <hi>Firſt,</hi> That Ordination to Prieſthood, gives Authority to the Ordained to Preach. A Truth ſo well known, and believed, that few will Liſt themſelves in the Army of Opponents, but ſuch as Gain by it. Moſt will wonder what Ordination means, if it gives not Authority to Preach. For it was uſed to fit the Presbyter for his whole Function, of which Preaching was a very Conſiderable Part.</p>
            <p>When our Saviour ordained his Miniſtry, He bid them <hi>go teach all Nations,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 28.19.</note> 
               <hi>and Baptize them.</hi> And in Conformity to Chriſts Inſtitution, the whole Catholick Church thus prepared Preachers by Ordination. And ſo doth the Church of <hi>England</hi> in her Office of Ordination, Require thoſe that are to be or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained to Promiſe, <hi>That they will give faithful Diligence alwaies to miniſter the Doctrine and Sacraments— And to teach the People committed to their Charge— And to drive away all Erroneous and ſtrange Doctrines.</hi> Without any previous Condition, <hi>If they ſhould be thereunto Licenſed.</hi> And farther the Ordainer ſaith, at Impoſition, of hands: <hi>Be thou a faithful Diſpenſer of the Word of God, and of his holy Sacraments.</hi> So that he is as much Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rized to Preaching, as to Adminſter Sacraments. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore may be as well forced to a new Licenſe for Adminiſtring Sacraments, as for the Preaching. But in truth, both theſe Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions are ſealed to him, under the moſt venerable Seal <hi>In the Name of the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If all this be thought, too little, to Authorize him to Preach, yet ſure when the Ordaining Biſhop delivers Him the Bible with theſe Words; <hi>Take thou Authority to Preach the Word of God, and to Miniſter the holy Sacraments, in the Congregation, where Thou ſhalt be lawfully appointed thereunto.</hi> Who can doubt but that He is as much Authorized to Preach in that Place, as to Adminiſter holy Sacrament. 'That is, as much as all the Licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in the World can give Him. For here the Ordaining Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, gives Him Authority to Preach and Adminiſter, under the moſt ſacred Circumſtances imaginable: being in Cathedra: in the preſence of God: and before the Aſſembly of Saints: at the Holy Altar: and Seals this Character, with the moſt tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendous Body and Blood of Chriſt. And what can a Scrole called a Licenſe do more than This? Is a Biſhop greater in his Study?. or Dining Room? than at the Church? or is his Table greater than the Altar? or Himſelf and Secretary, more venerable than the Congregation? what pitty is it that Ava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice or other unknown cauſe, ſhould run men into ſuch Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdities?</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:43918:4"/>
            <p>But They may ſay, though this be true, yet the Presbyter hath no Seal to Evidence this; ſo that He can't make it appear to all People where He comes. This we muſt Juſtly deny, for He receives Letters of Orders under the Biſhops hand and Seal; by which this Authority is manifeſted, as much as by the Licenſe. So then, we do with good Conſcience, and upon plain Evidence affirm, the Presbyter hath Licenſe to Preach by his Letters of Orders, and needs no more, if Officers need no Money.</p>
            <p>This Authority ſatisfied the holy Catholick Church for Four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen Centuries: amongſt whoſe Records we find no Licenſes to Preach beſides their Letters of Orders.</p>
            <p>We, hear of St. <hi>Cyprian</hi>'s Presbyter <hi>Didienſis,</hi> but read no other Title to Preach beſides his Letters of Orders. And when the <hi>Laurae</hi> were, ſettled in <hi>Aegypt,</hi> we yet find nothing but Ordination and the Prieſts Miſſion to dwell in a houſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced very near the Church: which anſwers well enough to our Inſtitution.</p>
            <p n="2">II. <hi>Secondly,</hi> That the Church for 1400 years, never required Incumbents on Benifices, to take Licenſes to Preach.</p>
            <p>This Propoſition being negative, admits of no other Proof, than that no notice of any Licenſes to Preach, hath come to our hands, after the beſt Search we could make about them. We ſee Ordination did Qualify for Preaching in the Church. And find that Biſhops did ſend their Presbyters abroad to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter Religion where they thought convenient. We find alſo a great many Requiſite Forms, or Letters uſed in many Caſes: as the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (which alſo were ſometimes called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> becauſe they did not only commend the Party that had Them, but alſo contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his diſmiſſion in Peace.) There were alſo <hi>Literae Formatae</hi> (called ſo I think from the Form of the Biſhops Seal put to them) as alſo <hi>Communicatoriae</hi> given to Chriſtians Travelling, that they might be received into the Catholick Communion, where they came. Theſe and a few others, we meet with in the Primitive times, as the <hi>Tractoriae</hi> which directed the Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers of Churches, and gave them ready Acceptance where they were ſent. And ſo ancient, that we find the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or Commendatory Letters mentioned by S. <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf as of common uſe in his time.<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.1. <hi>Can. Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>och.</hi> 7, 8.</note> Witneſs thoſe words of his <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> And in the Synod of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:43918:5"/>
               <hi>Antioch</hi> we ſee ſome others; but no where theſe Letters of Licenſe for Preaching. And if there were any ſuch, 'tis to be wonder'd at, that neither <hi>Bernardinus Ferarius</hi> that treated ſo minutely of the ancient Rights of Biſhops: nor <hi>Alcuinus, Ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larius,</hi> or any other of thoſe Antiquaries, that <hi>Charles</hi> the Great ſet on work, to ſearch the ancient cuſtoms of the Church: nor any other, of thoſe collected by <hi>Melchior Hittorpius,</hi> ſhould hit on them. We can't ſuſpect thoſe Authors of Ignorance, in the Church Canons and cuſtoms ſeeing it was a known Rule: <hi>Nulli Sacerdotum liceat ſuos Canones ignorare.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Grat. nulli diſt. <hi>38.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>We may add the Probability, that this Church of <hi>England,</hi> knew nothing of this Licenſe to Preach, in the time of Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop. <hi>Stratford An. Dom.</hi> 1342,<note place="margin">Lyndw. l. <hi>3</hi> tit <hi>22</hi> cap. Saeva &amp; &amp;c.</note> nor at any time before. For his Synod endeavoured to ſtop the Oppreſſions of the Clergy; and to Reſtrain the greedy appetites of the Officers; ſeeing the inferior Clergy groaning under their burdens, ready to joyn with the <hi>Wiclefiſts</hi> in their complaints. And therefore enume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated all the Seals and Writings then in uſe: and aſcertained the Fees, for them: but makes no mention of any Licenſes to Preach as diſtinct from Letters of Orders. They are thus reckoned. <hi>Pro Scriptura Literarum, Inquiſitionum, Inſtitutionum, vel Collationum, &amp; Commiſſionum ad inducendum, vel Certificato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rijs ipſarum in Beneficijs, ultra</hi> xij <hi>Denarios. Pro Literis vero cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juslibet Sacri Ordinis, ultra</hi> vj <hi>Denarios dicti Clerici per ſe vel per alios, non recipiant quovis modò.</hi> And farther to Evidence that the Synod intended to omit nothing then in uſe, they add that the Sewers, Porters, Grooms, nor Barbers ſhould require no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, giving this Reaſon for it, That the Ordinary ought to maintain his own Servants with fitting Wages. Now can any man (not quite deſerted of Reaſon) imagine this intent Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod forgat theſe Licenſes to Preach? Or may we not more reaſonably conclude, there was no Footſtep of any ſuch Practice then in uſe? And yet we ſhall ſoon hear of it, even in his time, tho' not required to be taken by any Incumbents.</p>
            <p n="3">III. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> That the Church Canons enjoyned all Incumbents to Preach under great Penalties; which ſurely they would not do if they were not qualified for it, without Licenſes. But the Canons proceed on a Suppoſition, that Ordination and Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion gave Title enough to furniſh out a Preacher for his Cure. It will not be neceſſary to ſhew the many Canons of <hi>Codex Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae univerſatis,</hi> ſeeing our own Church hath plenty enough.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:43918:5"/>But if any deſire it, he may conſult <hi>Photius</hi> his <hi>Nomo canon. tit.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 2. where He may be ſatisfied.</p>
            <p>For the Church of <hi>Englands</hi> zeal that way, we may conſult <hi>Stephen Langtons</hi> Decree, in the Council holden at <hi>Oxford Anno</hi> 1222, how earneſtly Preaching is urged on all Incumbents <hi>Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentis Concilij definitione diſtricte duximus injung endum, ut Rectores &amp; vicarij, Plebes ſibi commiſſas pabulo verbi Dei, ſecundum quòd fuit ijs inſpiratum, informare procurent, ne canes muti meritò judicentur: cùm latratu ſalubri a Caulis Dominicis Luporum ſpiritualium morſus non expellunt</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>So likewiſe <hi>John Peccham</hi> in a Conſtitution made at <hi>Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth An. Dom.</hi> 1281 <hi>Cap. Ignorantia Sacerdotum</hi> &amp;c. Impoſes this care on the Archdeacon to watch the Clergy concerning Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching. <hi>Quoties Archidiaconi invenerint Presbyteros, Inſtitutionem moralem populo minime praedicaſſe, ſen publicaſſe, toties eos arguant &amp; poena Canonica caſtigando ſupplere compellant, quod temere omiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſame Council alſo lays this charge on the Clergy. <hi>Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipimus, ut quilibet Sacerdos Plebi praeſidens, quater in Anno— per. vel per alium exponat populo vulgariter, quatuor decem Fidei Articu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los: Decem mandata Decalogi: Duo Praecepta Evangelij: Septem ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra miſericordiae: Septem mortalia peccata</hi> &amp;c. and gives, them a Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod how to do it. By which we may conclude, they were ſo far from Reſtraining their Clergy from Preaching; that they urged it by all good means they could. While we ſtrive to embaraſs that work, till ſo much money is paid for our leave to do it.</p>
            <p>'Tis true indeed, that if a Prieſt were a Stranger; that came out of <hi>Ireland, Wales,</hi> or <hi>Scotland,</hi> and for the ſame Reaſon, from any other Foreign Church, ſuch a one was forbidden to cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brate any Divine Offices in this Church: If he came without Commendatory or Dimiſſory Letters of his Ordinary (And e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially if there were any doubt of his Lawful Ordination) Unleſs He came with a Licenſe from the Dioceſan. This Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution was made under <hi>Walter Reynolds,</hi> in the Second Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil at <hi>Oxford Anno</hi> 1322, in theſe words <hi>Item praecipimus ne Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdotes ignoti, de quorum Ordinatione non conſtat ad Divinorum ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrationem diſerviendo Eccleſijs admittantur, niſi de</hi> Licentia <hi>Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copi Dioeceſani.</hi> Nor was it Lawful for the Dioceſan to give him that Licenſe, without Letters Teſtimonial and good. Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence that He was lawfully ordained.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:43918:6"/>
            <p>Here we ſee a Licenſe mentioned to be given by the Dioce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſan, but it was to a Foreigner. 2 To one that was no Incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent. 3. To one whoſe Ordination was doubted. 4. Twas a Licenſe <hi>ad celebrationem Divinorum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lynd. de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ler. pere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grinat. c. <hi>8</hi>
               </note> which the Gloſs interprets, to celebrate Maſs; the Canonical hours: and to adminiſter Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments: ſo that it was not a bare Licenſe to Preach. 5. The Reaſon of it was, That none below the Dignity of a Biſhop, might be truſted with the Judgment of Foreigners Pretences to holy Orders. Which therefore can make nothing to our Licenſes to Preach. There is another Proviſion concerning Chaplains celebration in any of our Churches, after <hi>Lollardiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me</hi> began to ſpread it ſelf; made in a Council at <hi>Oxford</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Thomas Arondel Anno</hi> 1408. in theſe words: <hi>Nullus Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellanus admittatur ad celebrandum, in aliqua Diaeceſi noſtrae Cantu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arienſis Provinciae, in quâ Oriundus ſive Ordinatus fuerit; niſi deferat ſecum Literas Ordinum ſuorum, atque Literas Commendatitias Dioece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſani ſui</hi> &amp;c. without which Orders and Commendatory Letters of the Biſhop, if any Rector, Vicar, or Curate, did permit him to celebrate, <hi>Permittens acriter puniatur.</hi> On which we may obſerve, 'Tis a Rule for Chaplains not Incumbents. 2. It enables them to celebrate Divine Service, as well as to Preach, and ſo accords not with our Licenſes.</p>
            <p n="4">IIII. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> When Licenſes were firſt introduced, the Church obliged no Incumbents to take theſe Licenſes to Preach. If they did Require it, we might expect to hear of them, either at Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, or Induction: but we hear of none in company with either of them.</p>
            <p>Firſt we hear of none at Inſtitution. There is a Conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on made at <hi>Lambeth</hi> under Archbiſhop <hi>Peccham,</hi> concerning the Inſtitution of an Incumbent, directing the Form of it, in theſe words: <hi>Statuimus u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> unusquiſque Epiſcopus, Clerico quem ad Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiam admittat, Literas Patentes ſuper ſua Admiſſione concedat. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter alia continentes, in quo conſiſtat Ordine: etiam quo Titulo, ad hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſmodi Beneficium admittatur</hi> &amp;c. Had that Council then thought Licenſes to Preach neceſſary, no doubt they had order'd them too. Seeing now the Incumbent was going to his Cure, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the obligation of the Canons to Preach, and Inſtruct his People.</p>
            <p>It ſeems the <hi>Gloſſator</hi> thought the Letters of Inſtitution thus drawn, were Title good enough, without any farther Licenſe
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:43918:6"/>to Preach: for He tells us <hi>Hae enim Literae in Beneficialibus haben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur loco Tituli.</hi> That this Inſtitution was his Title.</p>
            <p>Secondly, nor doth any thing concerning theſe Licenſes ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, when Mandats for Induction were enjoyn'd In the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil held at <hi>Oxford</hi> under the afore named <hi>John Stratford</hi> in the year 1343 (as many reckon) or 1342 (as the Manuſcript Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py in the <hi>Bedleian</hi> Library hath it) Mandats for Induction are mentioned; and the Rates of them ſet, to bound the Gripes of Avarice. But no mention is yet made of theſe Licenſes to Preach. The Conſtitution is <hi>Sacro approbante Concilio ſtatuimus, ut hi qui admiſſos ad Beneficia Eccleſiaſtica, ad Mandatum Superio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris tenentur inducere; pro indunctione hujuſmodi facienda Sumptibus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tententur moderatis. Videlicet ſi Archi Diaconus Inducat</hi> xl <hi>Denarijs. Si ſuus Officialis duorum ſolidorum perceptione.</hi> Providing, that if either take more than is there allowed, for the Induction,<note place="margin">Conſt. Provin. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>3.</hi> tit. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> or <hi>propter Literas Certificatorias</hi> (meaning the indorſed Certificates of Execution) They are to be ſuſpended <hi>ab Officio, et ingreſſu Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae</hi> Till they Refund the Extorted money, to the Party wronged.</p>
            <p>We may (without doing violence to our Reaſon) believe, That bounds had been ſet, to the Rates of Licenſes alſo, had there, been any ſuch things then in uſe. And the rather becauſe the ſame Council, under the ſame Prelate, complain'd heavily of the great Exactions then on the Clergy. And therefore ſixt the charge of every Seal then in uſe, for Incumbents to take,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Conſt.</hi> 1.3. <hi>tit.</hi> 22.</note> as appears by their Conſtitution <hi>Saeva et miſerabilis Cupiditas</hi> &amp;c. which hath been already touched. In which they Decree againſt both Biſhops, Archdeacons, and their Clerks; That they ſhall not take for any Writings above twelve pence. Nor for any Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Orders above ſix pence. And for Sealing nothing at all. If any Clerk took more, he was to refund double. If he were a Beneficed man, he was ſuſpended <hi>ab officio &amp; Beneficio.</hi> If a Lay man he was to be ſuſpended <hi>ab ingreſſu Eccleſiae,</hi> till ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction made.</p>
            <p>'Tis very probable, That ſuch Conſtitutions of our own, and the Catholick Church, cauſed that Learned and tender Prelate Biſhop <hi>Bedell,</hi>
               <note place="margin">v. Burnets <hi>life of</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del.</note> to write the Letters of Orders and Inſtitutions himſelf as the worthy Dr. <hi>Burnet,</hi> the preſent Biſhop of <hi>Sarum</hi> teſtifies of him.</p>
            <p>The ſame Council condeſcended to take notice, That Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deacons would not ſuffer Incumbents, to adminiſter Divine ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, in the Cures they were admitted to, till they had paid them
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:43918:7"/>ſix pence, for matriculation, in their Rolls of Call. Which payment that Council reduced to one penny as formerly it was. And is it probable they ſhould omit a Licenſe (if any) that remembred ſuch a Trifle?</p>
            <p>And farther to ſhew the diligence of the Gloſs on that De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree, that nothing be forgotten; It blames thoſe Ordinaries, that will Reviſe their Clergies Orders, Inſtitutions <hi>&amp;c.</hi> for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit: though they have peruſed and ſatisfied themſelves about them before.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, In the firſt appearances of any Licenſes to Preach, we find the Incumbents of Churches, not charged to take them. But their Right to Preach, by virtue of their Inſtitution; and their Obligation thereto, is acknowledged.</p>
            <p>The firſt Occaſion of forbidding Preaching, without Licenſe, that we meet withall, was in regard to <hi>Wickliffes</hi> Doctrins, then much ſpread in <hi>England:</hi> under the name of <hi>Lollards.</hi> Not ſo called <hi>e Lolio</hi> from <hi>Durnell,</hi> as <hi>Godolphin</hi> and <hi>Lyndwood,</hi> and other <hi>Civilians</hi> fancy. As if they were the plague of the Church, as Darnell is of Wheat. But from one <hi>Walter Lollard</hi> a <hi>German,</hi> the firſt noted to profeſs thoſe Doctrins, about the year 1315. This Sect ſpread much in the Reign of <hi>Edw.</hi> III. and increaſed to the times of <hi>Hen.</hi> V. whereof <hi>John Wickliffe</hi> Rector of <hi>Lut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terworth</hi> was the greateſt Promotor, in <hi>England.</hi> Of whoſe Doctrine Forty Five Articles ſtand condemned in the Eighth Seſſion of the Council of <hi>Conſtance.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pacher. de Concil l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> As likewiſe at <hi>London An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no</hi> 1382. And at length, the Profeſſors of it were condemned to puniſhment, by Act of Parliament, made 2 <hi>Henry</hi> V. <hi>cap.</hi> 7. And <hi>Thomas Arondell</hi> Arch Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> decreed many things againſt them,<note place="margin">Conſt. l. <hi>5.</hi> tit. <hi>5.</hi> de hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret.</note> in a Council held at <hi>Oxford, Anno Dom.</hi> 1408. And Pope <hi>Martin</hi> the Fifth <hi>Anno</hi> 1429 raiſed a Cruſado againſt Them, under the Conduct of <hi>Henry</hi> Cardinal of S. <hi>Euſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bius</hi> and (if my memory fail not) then Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now ſeeing that many Foreigners, and Laymen, Catechizers, and Lecturers, took upon them to Preach theſe Doctrines; a Conſtitution was made, in the ſaid Council at <hi>Oxford</hi> 1408, That none ſhould Preach without Licenſe.</p>
            <p>The words of the Decree are; <hi>Ordinamus quod nullus Soecula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris aut Regularis, ad praedicandum verbum Dei, a jure Scripto mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me authoriſatus: privilegiove ſpeciali munitus, Officium ceu exercitium proedicationis ejuſdem verbi Dei, in ſe aſſumat. Populove aut Clero, quoviſmodò praedicet, in Latino Sermone ſeu vulgari, in Ecchſia aut Extra</hi> &amp;c. Unleſs He preſent himſelf to the Dioceſan, and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:43918:7"/>undergo his Examination: and being found fit, he be ſent to Preach, to one or more certain Pariſhes, as the Ordinary ſhall think fit. And 'tis order'd that no Rector or Vicar is to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit any to Preach, unleſs he ſhow his Miſſion, or ſpecial Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; How he appears qualified for the ſervice of Preaching. <q>Or if he come from the Dioceſan, He is to ſhew his Letters under Seal.</q> But this concerned thoſe that were not autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſed <hi>Jure Scripto,</hi> as all Incumbents were; And Friers <hi>Praedicants,</hi> and <hi>Minors</hi> were authoriſed to Preach by ſpecial Priviledg, and the Gloſs thinks <hi>Auguſtinians</hi> and <hi>Carmelites</hi> were ſo too. So that it did not reach them. But it did reach all other Friers, Strangers, Lecturers, Catechiſers, and the like.</p>
            <p>That Incumbents were not intended, is plain from the Excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Jure Scripto minimè authoriſati,</hi> for they had their Authority under Seal, and by the Canons were bound to Preach. And the following Clauſe cleers it: <q>
                  <hi>Curatum vero perpetuum, miſſum intelligimus a Jure, ad Locum et populum Curae ſuae.</hi> And it farther adds concerning Curates that might be changed; <hi>Sacerdotes vero Parochiales ſeu Vicarii temporales, et non perpetui, in formâ ſupradictâ non miſſi, in Eccleſijs illis, in quibus hujuſmodi officia gerunt Illa ſola ſimpliciter praedicent, quae in Conſtitutione Provinciali, a bonae memoriae Johanne Praedeceſſore noſtro, in Capite Ignorantia Sacerdotum continentur expreſsè.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Now becauſe men might imagine, this new Licenſe to Preach was order'd to be taken, on purpoſe to get more Fees; 'Tis wiſely provided by the Council, that it ſhould be granted, <hi>Sine aliquali Exactione pecuniae</hi> without any manner of Fee. <hi>Celeriter expediunter, et gratis,</hi> ſays the Conſtitution.</p>
            <p>And then the Council provides, If any ſuch Preach, without theſe Letters: or if any ſay, the Church hath not power to lay on this Reſtraint, he incurs the Sentence of the greater Excommunication: and is to be treated as a <hi>Heretick,</hi> or <hi>Shiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick</hi> having all his goods confiſcated. Yea the place where ſuch Preaching is held (if not ſtopt by the People) is put un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Interdict.</p>
            <p>From this Conſtitution we may draw theſe Concluſions, 1 That this was a new Law, not impoſed before, to take Licenſes to Preach. 2 That Incumbents are declared to have power to Preach <hi>Jure Scripto</hi> by Law, in their Cures. 3 That ſome others had Right to Preach, without taking theſe Licenſes <hi>Privilegio Speci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ali:</hi> as Friers <hi>Praedicants, Minors, Auguſtinians</hi> and <hi>Carmelites.</hi> 4 That theſe Licenſes were to be granted by the <hi>Dioceſian</hi> Biſhop,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:43918:8"/>and not <hi>per inferiorem Epiſcopo,</hi> namely not by any Archdeacon, Chancellor, Commiſſary, Official or the like. 5 That. theſe, Licenſes were to be taken by Strangers Lecturers <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but not by Incumbents, nor their temporary Curates. 6 That theſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbents or temporary Curates were to Admit, or Refuſe ſuch Preachers, in their Cures as they ſhould find their Licenſes to be. 7 That thoſe who were bound to take Licenſes to Preach, were not to pay one Farthing for them. This part of the Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion well obſerved<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> would end all Diſputes, about <hi>Parochial Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſan,</hi> and <hi>Provincial</hi> Licenſes. 8 It ſhews where this wiſe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil Judged Licenſes to Preach neceſſary: Namely for all that had not perpetual, or temporary Cure of Souls. For to them that had ſuch Cures, Ordination gave them <hi>Jus ad Rem.</hi> Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to Preach, in any part of the holy Catholick Church: But Inſtitution gave them <hi>Jus in Re,</hi> a Right to Preach actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to the People of their Cures: And to the temporary Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates by virtue of the Incumbents Deputation. As alſo to neceſſary Aſſiſtants in caſe of Sickneſs, or neceſſary Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence.</p>
            <p>The Friers Titles are not neceſſary here to be ſpoken to, becauſe this Church of <hi>England</hi> is troubled with none of them, that come to challenge any Right.</p>
            <p n="5">V. <hi>Fifthly,</hi> If the Canons of this Church did ever oblige In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbents to take Licenſes to Preach. It was upon very ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary, and Accidental Conſiderations. Such as alſo forced the Church to compoſe books of <hi>Homilies,</hi> for the uſe of Incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bents that could not Preach.</p>
            <p>Upon the Reformation, there were great Numbers of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbents, brought into the Church in the time of Popery that were not able to Preach: who yet turned Proteſtants and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed to the Doctrine, and Diſcipline of this Church as far as they were able; whom the Piety and Charity of thoſe times thought not fit to caſt out of their Livings; becauſe they thought fit to give them ſome Reſpect for their Conformity: and to ſave the <hi>Pariſhes</hi> from the burthen of their mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance: and thoſe poor Prieſts from periſhing through wants: and becauſe they had not Learned men enough to put into their places: and becauſe they would not willfully force, by their violent treatment, ſo many men, to act againſt the Safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Church and State; which had Enemies enough, both at home and abroad, wherefore they were permitted to continue in
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:43918:8"/>their Living, and to celebrate Divine Service: but were never forbid to Preach: yet when the Church found them able (by their Study and Induſtry, and often hearing Sermons) to Preach; They wiſely took that opportunity, to try their Parts, and to bring them under Subſcriptions, to uſe the Proteſtants method, by requiring them to take Licenſes to Preach, when they thought themſelves able.</p>
            <p>One may juſtly wonder how ſuch ignorant Men came into the Church:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Con. Carth.</hi> 6. c. 19.</note> conſidering how importunate the Primitive Canons are for Prieſts Preaching: inſomuch that the laſt Council of <hi>Carthage</hi> enjoyns it every day, or at leaſt every Lords day. And if the Presbyter were ſick, the Deacon is order'd to read a Homily to the People. And that S. <hi>Ambroſe, Chryſoſtom,</hi> and <hi>Auguſtines</hi> Works ſhew that they Preacht all Faſts and Feaſts, as well as Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>days; and often every day, and many times twice a day. But this change muſt be Attributed to the guidance of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, in which Preaching fell early into contempt: for <hi>Sozo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi> obſerves the difference of that Church from all others,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Soz. l.</hi> 7. c. 19.</note> in this matter. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which was in the Reign of <hi>Valentinian</hi> and <hi>Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius.</hi> And leaſt any ſhould think <hi>Sozomen</hi> miſtaken in the Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of <hi>Rome,</hi> he may find the ſame Affirmed by <hi>Caſſiodore</hi> in his <hi>Tripartite</hi> Hiſtory, who lived in <hi>Rome,</hi> and could not be Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of their ſervices. 'Tis true <hi>Valeſius</hi> thinks this cuſtome alter'd in Pope <hi>Leo,</hi> who did Preach to the People; but one Swallow makes no Summer: He himſelf looks Irregular for his pains. You may know that that Church holds <hi>Preaching</hi> to be no part of the Eſſence of <hi>Prieſthood:</hi> for they account, <hi>Poteſtatem offerendi verum corpus Chriſti &amp; remittendi peccata,</hi> the power of offering the very body of Chriſt in the Euchariſt, and of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of Sins, to make up the formality of Prieſthood. And accordingly <hi>Anathematize</hi> ſuch as ſay, <hi>Qui non Praedicant,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cone. Trid. Seſs <hi>23.</hi> de Sacr. ordin. <hi>c. 1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>prorſus non eſſe Sacerdotes:</hi> one may be apt to ſuſpect thoſe to be of the ſame mind, that judge a Prieſt in his place may not Preach with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out taking out a New Licenſe ſo to do. We deny not but a Man may be a Prieſt that can't Preach in reſpect of Age, Sickneſs, or the like: but deny him to be a Prieſt of Chriſts Inſtitution, that hath not power to Preach, if he be able: becauſe Chriſt order'd all that he ſent to Preach and Baptize. And if you read on, the next Seſſion of that Council of <hi>Trent,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ib. ſeſs <hi>24.</hi> de Refor. <hi>cap. 4.</hi>
               </note> they ſeem more for Preaching than our Proteſtant Viſitors; for they ſay <hi>Praedicationis munus Epiſcoporum praecipuum eſt:</hi> and command all to Preach <hi>ſaltem
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:43918:9"/>omnibus dominicis &amp; ſollennibus feſtis diebus. Et tempore Quadrageſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mali, et Adventus, quotidie vel ſaltem tribus in hebdomade diebus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the Hiſtory of the Council of <hi>Trent</hi> will tell you, whence this new Flame, of Preaching was rais'd; intimating that Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing was loſt in Cathedrals, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> nor did any but Regulars keep it up,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hiſt. Con. Trent.</hi> l. 2. p. 173.</note> till <hi>Anno</hi> 1546, when it was raiſed again, by certain Rules of Reformation, paſs'd in the <hi>Trent</hi> Council, on <hi>June</hi> 17th. the ſame Year; upon the loud Accuſations <hi>and Complaints of all Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> both Popiſh and Proteſtant for a Reformation.</p>
            <p>Yet that Church ſeems to have an aking Tooth againſt it to this day, which may be gueſſed, from the Scornful reproaches caſt on the Preachers, by ſome of them, of whom we ſhall only inſtance in <hi>Becanus</hi> a <hi>Jeſuite,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bec.</hi> c. <hi>Gard.</hi> pag. 794.</note> ſeeing his immodeſty knows no Bounds in his Diſpute with <hi>Gardius,</hi> he tells him. <hi>Quamvis modeſtiae Pallio ſe obtegat Gardius, Praedicanticam naturam exuere non poſſe.</hi> Again, <hi>Hanc Praerogativam</hi> (ſcilicet ineptiendi) <hi>Praedicanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus relinquo.</hi> So he charges him <hi>imperitia novi Praedicantis.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Id.</hi> 1. c. §. 16. p. 17. <hi>Id.</hi> § 73. <hi>Id.</hi> § 170. <hi>Id.</hi> c. 3. § 117.</note> And farther, <hi>Ita antiqui Patres id ſtatuunt: ſi tu cum vulgo Praedicantium aliter ſentis per me licet.</hi> Again <hi>notae ſunt Praedicantium Impoſturae, ut facile caveri et contemni queant.</hi> So again <hi>novellus aliquis Praedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cans ſuſſuratur argumenta ex Bellarmino.</hi> By which and many other ſuch like paſſages; one may diſcern their bitterneſs againſt Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, as a moſt ridiculous Employment; yet S. <hi>Paul Magnifies,</hi> or rather Glorifies <hi>this Office.</hi> And tells us <hi>by this folliſhneſs of Preaching,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.13. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.21. 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.17.</note> 
               <hi>God intends to ſave ſome.</hi> And 'twas the Apoſtles main buſineſs, as that great Apoſtle notes, <hi>For Chriſt ſent me not to Baptize, but to Preach the Goſpel.</hi> By which it appears that Preaching was not only an eſſential part of a Prieſt, but is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to Sacraments themſelves. So that a Jeſuite follows Jeſus in his Name, but his Sentiments are vaſtly different, and often contrary; for Chriſt ſent the Preachers, and the Jeſuite derides them.</p>
            <p>If any doubt of the Ignorance of the <hi>Roman</hi> Clergy,<note place="margin">Id. Con. Hard. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pol. <hi>p. 622.</hi>
               </note> at the Reformation, they may ſee it proved beyond Exception, in the learned <hi>Jewel</hi> againſt <hi>Harding;</hi> in truth Learning made ſo great a fall in the ſixth Century, that the prime Men of the World, had very little of it. Even <hi>Theodorick</hi> King of <hi>Italy,</hi> and <hi>Juſtin</hi> in <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Amarcel in Addit.</hi> p. 669. <hi>Greg.</hi> op. I. 9. ep. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>9. <hi>id.</hi> 16. ep. 29.</note> could not write their own Names: as <hi>Veles</hi> in <hi>Ammianus Marcellinus,</hi> ſhews the greateſt of Popes <hi>Gregory</hi> the great, candedly confeſſes to <hi>Euſebius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Theſſaly,</hi> that he underſtood not a word of Greek, <hi>nos nec Graecum novimus;</hi> ſo alſo in another Epiſtle he ſays, <hi>Graeca Linguae neſcius.</hi> And ſome great
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:43918:9"/>Men in the Church knew not Latin neither, as <hi>Paulus Jovins</hi> notes of <hi>Riarius</hi> the Praeſident of the Conclave of <hi>Cardinals,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jov. vit. Lev. x. l. <hi>3.</hi> p. <hi>127.</hi> Long. ad an <hi>1389.</hi>
               </note> that <hi>Aetatis honore, Sacerdotijs atque opibus, caeteros omnes anteibat, quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam Ei deerant Literae atque eae Virtutes quae Sacerdotem exornant. Boniface</hi> the IX. Pope, <hi>fuit pane illiteratus</hi> ſays <hi>Langius.</hi> That <hi>Julius</hi> 3 underſtood no more Latin than a Soldier. There fore the Canon calls the Popes <hi>Doctores Authoritate non Scientia.</hi> Doctors by their place not by their Learning, which gives ſome colour for the Engliſh Proverb; that he can write no more than the Pope of <hi>Rome.</hi> Poor <hi>Heriman</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Babenberg</hi> was, ſays <hi>Langius, expers Literarum,</hi> and unfortunatly charged by one of his Canons,<note place="margin">Lamb. ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net Chro. ad an. <hi>1075.</hi>
               </note> that he could not Conſtrue one verſe in the Pſalmody, was (ſays <hi>Lambertus Schafnaburgenſis</hi>) depoſed by the Pope from his Biſhoprick, but continued a Prieſt. Yet <hi>Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> the great was more indulging, for he confirmed <hi>Ruſticus</hi> Elect Biſhop of <hi>Ancona, et ſi Pſalmos ignoraret.</hi> It ſeems Popes lookt aſquint on Learning as dangerous to their ſpiritual-worldly Dominion; for <hi>Paul</hi> II. call'd all that ſtudied Philoſophy Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks. And forbad the Citizens of <hi>Rome</hi> to keep their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to School longer than to write and read, <hi>Satis eſſe dicens ſi legire et ſcribere didiciſſent;</hi> which <hi>Platina</hi> notes in his life; the Chronologer remarks,<note place="margin">Lang. ad an <hi>1389.</hi>
               </note> That when <hi>Chryſolaras Bizantinus</hi> came to teach <hi>Greek</hi> in <hi>Rome</hi> (which was about 1389) the <hi>Greek</hi> tongue had been diſuſed there for 700 years laſt paſt. St. <hi>Francis</hi> alſo (it ſeems) was a great ſtickler againſt Learning for he curſt Frier <hi>John,</hi> for going to <hi>Bononia</hi> for Learning;<note place="margin">Lang. ad an. <hi>1254.</hi>
               </note> ſaying <hi>Se malle Fratres ſuos, magis orare quam Legere;</hi> as <hi>Langius</hi> reports it of him. One may ſee to what Barbarity the World was come, by the Canons that were made in favour of Ignorance: as that <hi>Sancti loquentes per Barbarimos non ſunt irridendi.</hi> V. <hi>de Conſecrat: Diſt.</hi> 4. c. <hi>retulerunt</hi> and again <hi>Epiſcopi errantes in Grammatica, non ſunt a Sapientibus deridendi.</hi> 38 <hi>Diſt. c. quamvis</hi> &amp;c In purſuance of the deſign, of theſe and ſuch like Canons, zealous <hi>Langius</hi> falls fowl on <hi>Eraſmus,</hi> for deriding the well meaning Cardinal <hi>Hugo</hi>'s ſtrange miſtakes, about the meaning and derivation of <hi>Greek</hi> Words: but thereby proves the Barbarity of the times,<note place="margin">Lang. ad an. <hi>1250.</hi>
               </note> ſaying of S. <hi>Hugo; In ea tempora incidiſſet, quae politiores Literas, praecipue Graecas, totam et per Galliam, et per Germaniam, prorſus incompertas &amp; inauditas habuerant.</hi> You may gueſs by this little, how dimm the Light was that guided the World, till the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, and what wooden Tools thoſe Sr. <hi>Johns</hi> were that then ſupplied the place of Burning and ſhining Lamps.</p>
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:43918:10"/>
            <p>We will propound but one grave diſpute, upon this Subject, and ſo leave it; that we nauſeat not the Reader. The famous <hi>Aventine</hi> in his Annals of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> tells us of a Prieſt of that Country who being wholly ignorant of the Latin Tongue,<note place="margin">Avent. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal. l. <hi>3.</hi> p. mihi <hi>172.</hi>
               </note> did yet baptize <hi>In nomine Patria Filia et Spirita Sancta.</hi> A Queſtion grew upon it whether it was good Baptiſm or not? <hi>Vargilius</hi> the Biſhop Juſtified it: but <hi>Boniface</hi> of <hi>Mentz</hi> utterly condemned it. The whole matter referred to Pope <hi>Zachary</hi> who (alwaies pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful to the Blind) approved it, as done with a good Intention to Baptize.</p>
            <p>But here the Reader muſt beware, That he conclude not that a groſs thick darkneſs covered all the Earth; for there were ſtill ſome ſtars in every Horizon, tho' very few. Some ſparks of Learning ſurvived the deluge, which have been blown up to the Bonfires we ſee in all places: but the Profeſſors were <hi>Rari nantes in Gurgite vaſto.</hi> Rare as Phaenixes, one in an Age. The Church required little more than mumming and Maſſing, and Received leſs than Required.</p>
            <p>Now as there were many illiterate men brought into the Church that Conformed, and were Continued: ſo the Reformers, had not able men enough, to ſupply the Places of thoſe Few that laid down their Calling.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Can. of</hi> 1603 <hi>can.</hi> 45, 46.</note> They were therefore forced to make plain honeſt, but Ignorant men Incumbents, who were not then able to Preach, but were admoniſhed to attend their Studies: to Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrate Divine ſervice; once a month to get an able Preacher in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their Pariſhes: and at other times to read a Homily. For their ſakes in the preſent defect, the new Canons were made: That before they ventured to Preach, they ſhould come to their Biſhops: undergo an Examination of their Ability: and make their due Subſcriptions, and ſo Receive their Licenſes from the Biſhops.</p>
            <p>This method of dealing with weak Incumbents,'tis probable the Reformers took from the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Seſſ. <hi>23.24</hi> Hiſt. trent. l. <hi>2.</hi> p. <hi>174.</hi>
               </note> who Decreed much the ſame Things: as may be ſeen by comparing the 23 and 24 Seſſions of that Council with the Hiſtory of the Council <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no</hi> 1546. where they Require Licenſes to be taken for the preſent Exigent of Affairs. Judging Twilight better then quite Dark, and a Ruſh Candle to be preferred before none: That the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digal were better Eat Husks, than die for hunger. And the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the houſhold of Faith to feed on Coarſe Fare, than have no Food at all.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:43918:10"/>
            <p>Here we ought to Conſider, That the Church at Inſtitution gave Incumbents Authority to Preach in their Cures; and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver prohibited them. But long inveterate Cuſtom of Maſſing, had taught the Inſtitutor not to regard the Incumbents ability. And the Inſtituted, not to fit himſelf for a Duty that none practiſed. Yet would it appear ſtrange, to bid the Ordained Prieſt, not to Preach in his Cures ſeeing he was ordained to that very End, if Chriſts Miniſter. But they were ſatisfied of the Incumbents inability for the preſent, and ſo Required it not of him, till better able. 2. That the non Preaching Incumbents, were bound by Canon, to <hi>procure Sermons to be Preacht in their Cure once every Month at leaſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Can.</hi> 46.</note> 
               <hi>Concionem per Concionatorem legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time approbatum haberi procurabit</hi> &amp;c. But can any man believe, the Church would grant men leave, to procure Sermons, or Preachers, yet would not truſt them to preach themſelves, had they been able? 'Tis an allow'd Rule <hi>Qui facit per Alium, facit per ſe.</hi> So that we may conclude; It was not their not taking Licenſes made them uncapable of Preaching; but their inabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to perform it. Inſomuch that the Church thought good, to wait their Progreſs Studies, till they could perform it. 3. It is alſo plain, that Incumbents were not bound to take Licenſes to Preach before theſe Canons made, becauſe then (ſome of them at leaſt) had had them before hand; and ſo need not come before the Biſhop for them; which had ſpoiled the whole Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject. 4. we may perceive too, that the <hi>Trent</hi> Canons, order'd theſe Licenſes; to be given <hi>gratis:</hi> as we noted before, of our former Canons, that related not to Incumbents. Had the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons of 1603 made the ſame Proviſion; 'Tis odds that we had heard nothing of them to this Day:<note place="margin">Hiſt. Trent. l. <hi>2.164.</hi>
               </note> Biſhops Chancellors and Comiſſaries would not have quarrelled who ſhould have granted Them: ſince men are ſeldom keen, to cut out themſelves work, without wages.</p>
            <p>It appears therefore upon the whole matter, That if there be any Canons, Requiring Incumbents to take Licenſes to Preach, They are grounded upon ſpecial Reaſons, and particular Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions that are extraordinary, and ſo can't found an Ordinary Rule. If the Ground fail the Superſtructure muſt alſo fail. We adminiſter not the ſame Remedy but where is the ſame diſeaſe. Thanks be to God, the Biſhop hath choice of able Preachers as well as able Prieſts: and can at Inſtitution provide for one as well as the other. Why ſhould that be done at twice that can and ought to be done at once? <hi>Fruſtra fit per plura</hi> &amp;c. A
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:43918:11"/>Prieſt implies a man that can Pray and Preach. Why ſhould any put aſunder what Chriſt joyn'd together. By the Canon of Canons a Preiſt muſt be <hi>apt to teach:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 32.</note> as to pray, and adminiſter Divine Service. Men expect not freſh Grace to every diſtinct Diſh, that comes to Table; it ſuffices to conſecrate the whole Dinner at once. If we will take the Services apart, where will Covetouſneſs end? Why may not Clergy be forc't to take one Licenſe to Preach? another to Pray? another to Marry? ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to Bury? <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">VI. But to Proceed <hi>Sixthly,</hi> That Licenſes to Preach, add not, nor diminiſh, to or from the Title to any Benefice. This Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe is a thing ſo extrinſick, and uſeleſs to a Divine, that he knows not what uſe to make of it. His Ordination gave him Authority to Preach, and his Inſtitution appointed out the Place: what then doth this Licenſe ſerve for? Is He more an Incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent when he hath it, than he was without it? Both Comon Lawyers, and Civilians agree, that the Incumbents Tide is as good without it as with it. So that It gives them Licenſe only to pay for it.</p>
            <p>It would be tedious without profit, to tranſcribe, what Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Lawyers ſay, makes a good Title to a Benifice. We may poſitively ſay that they do not ſo much as name theſe Licenſes in ſtating the Title: nor do we hear the Civilians introducing them, as neceſſary to make a Title. To cut this matter ſhort, we will vouch one, with his <hi>Nomo Canon,</hi> to ſpeak for all; ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving joyn'd the Comon Law and Civil together: namely Dr. <hi>Godolphin,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reper. Law. cap.</hi> 17. §. 4.</note> who in his <hi>Repertorium Canonicum</hi> twice ſtates the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbents Titles 1 under the Title Parſon. He ſays no man can be a Parſon unleſs 1 He be in holy Orders. 2 four and twenty years, of age. 3 unleſs he be admitted by Inſtitution. 4 and Inducted. 5 unleſs he ſubſcribe the uſe of the book of Comon Prayer, and take the Biſhops Certificate of it. 6 un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs he within two months after Inſtitution and Induction, read the 39 Articles in his Church, on ſome Sunday <hi>tempore Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinorum,</hi> and declare before the Congregation, his unfeigned Aſſent, and conſent, to every thing conteined and required in them. And on the ſame Sunday read the ſervice of the day. In all which we hear nothing of this Licenſe to Preach. And his 5th refers only to Incumbents <hi>Aug.</hi> 24. 1662.</p>
            <p>Again the ſame Author,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Id. c.</hi> 28. §. 1.</note> in his Title Incumbent, ſhews four things Preparatory to the being a Compleat Incumbent. 1 The
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:43918:11"/>Patrons Praeſentation. 2 The Biſhops Admiſſion after Examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, making a Record of his name. 3 The Clerks Inſtitution. 4 The Clerks Induction. Theſe things, and peacable poſſeſſion for ſix Months, is a <hi>Plenarty pro hâc vice,</hi> and barrs any in a <hi>Quare Impedit.</hi> So that then Licenſes are neither antecedently neceſſary, to the ſettlement of an Incumbent: nor conſequently neceſſary to continue him in his Cure. What then ſhould move ſome men to urge theſe Licenſes; but what makes the Mare to go?</p>
            <p n="7">
               <hi>Seventhly,</hi> That the forcing Incumbents to take Licenſes, was of no benefit to the Church: nor to the Officers, but the Fees. This will appear,</p>
            <p n="1">1. By conſidering that Licenſes to Preach can't bind from Preaching falſe Doctrine, more than Subſcription to the 39 Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles will do: for what virtue is there in the Biſhops, or Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellors hand and wax, more than in our own Subſcription and Promiſe, to keep us Orthodox? Is that an Amulet againſt He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſy? nor can we ſee any virtue in it, to reſtrain Preaching againſt Conformity or Ceremonies, more than in our Subſcription to the three Articles in the 36 Canon, of the Canons made 1603. Beſides, the Laws of this Realm back, and enforce the obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our Subſcriptions; but take no notice of theſe intruded Licenſes as arbitrarily impoſed on a tame and couching Clergy.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Clergy may as effectually be corrected, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed from ill, Heretical, or Shiſmatical Preaching, without Licenſes as with them. For the Incumbent may be convened, admoniſhed, Reprov'd; and upon <hi>non</hi> Amendment, may be ſuſpended; and if contumatious Excommunicated: and ſtanding ſo for Forty daies, may be deprived. And if he ſtill perſiſt in Hereſy or Schiſm, be diliver'd over to the Secular Arme. If they will give him Liberty of Preaching, they are an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to God for all the Miſcheifs he doth, but the Church is clear.</p>
            <p>This way muſt be taken with Licenſes too, as well as with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out. For tho' men dote on them, they can no more ſtrangle wicked Preaching than other Seals and Subſcriptions: nor ſo much, being not warranted by Law. And in truth this was the only Remedy the Primitive Church had, to ſuppreſs all their Hereſies and Schiſms: convening the Offender before the Dioceſan: if that cured not the malady, then before the Synod; where the Hereſy or Schiſm was declared, and the Party re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed or Excommunicated: and the People admoniſhed to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw from Him.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:43918:12"/>
            <p>This Courſe may be taken ſtill againſt all ſorts of Sectaries, that by Baptiſm were once made members of our Church. Who either will not take Licenſes, or can't be reformed by them.</p>
            <p>If it be ſaid that, however Licenſes are a more expedite way, becauſe 'tis but taking them away from ſuch as Preach Hereſy, or Schiſm. We may anſwer. 1 They muſt firſt be convicted by due proceſs, before they are puniſhed; for <hi>Hallafax</hi> Law is not well reliſhed in <hi>England.</hi> So that the other method will be as nimble as this. 2 If Licenſes are <hi>durante beneplacito,</hi> they are too haughty for any thing leſs than the Papal Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to give, and too ſlaviſh for a Miniſter of Chriſt to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive. 3 If teaching be an eſſential part of Prieſthood, 'tis impoſſible to take it away, but by depoſing the Prieſt: and that is the puniſhment directed in the 38 Canon. 4 'Tis pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable ſuch ill men would not deliver up their Licenſes, nor if they did, would hold themſelves thereby diſabled to Preach: ſeeing (generally ſpeaking) all Clergy believe themſelves au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoriſed to Preach by Ordination: and the place aſſigned out by Inſtitution: and think Licenſes as uſeleſs Tools impoſed upon Incumbents of Livings: ſo that the Cure would not be ſo quick as imagined. 5 Add to this that it would look ill, to ſee an unpreaching Miniſtry; neither ſuſpended <hi>ab Officio,</hi> nor <hi>Beneficio,</hi> but <hi>a parte Officij;</hi> a term as uncouth among <hi>Civilians,</hi> as <hi>Chagrine</hi> amongſt the <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The dreadfull Rebellion of 1640 did give us a ſad Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience of the little ſervice theſe Licenſes did the Church. for the Lecturers (to whom they were neceſſary) were ſo far from being confined by them, That they were the loudeſt and ſhrilleſt Trumpets of the War. The Lecturers Holy water ſwell'd the Flouds of the Church and States calamity. Their Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pits were the bellowing Drums, on which they beat the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larms of War.<note place="margin">Burnet <hi>Ref. p.</hi> 2. <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>pag.</hi> 160.</note> They were ſet up, ſays the Hiſtory of the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation in 1550: and <hi>Barrow</hi> againſt <hi>Gifford</hi> tells you why. <q>The Lecturer was brought in to anſwer the <hi>Geneva</hi> Platform, that we may have a Doctor beſides a Paſtor. He calls him a Sectary Teacher:<note place="margin">V. Barrow <hi>againſt</hi> Giff. <hi>pag.</hi> 136.</note> a Roving <hi>Stipendiary Predicant</hi>— brought in by ſuch of a Pariſh as have Itching Ears — From theſe ariſe the <hi>Schiſms</hi> and <hi>Sects</hi> in the Church of <hi>England</hi>— They are Sighers for Reformation, and Conſcience Botchers— They ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce and diſtract the People, ſome to this Preacher ſome to that, from their own Pariſhes and Churches: calls them bats
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:43918:12"/>being neither <hi>Laiety,</hi> becauſe <hi>Ordained;</hi> nor <hi>Clergy</hi> becauſe they had no <hi>Benefices.</hi>
               </q> Of whom He gives a large (and no doubt a true) Account, having been bred under them, till he turn'd <hi>Browniſt,</hi> and fell into the Rigid Separation.</p>
            <p>'Tis probable, that Holy Biſhop and Martyr <hi>Ridley,</hi> foreſaw the danger that would ariſe, from ſuch Licentiates, that He ſet himſelf ſo heartily againſt them, as the Hiſtorian notes, as alſo did King <hi>Edwards</hi> wiſe Privy Council, forbidding the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,<note place="margin">Burnet <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </note> to have any thing but Prayers on the Week daies.</p>
            <p>It were not difficult to ſhew, that the <hi>Smectymnuan</hi> Party, and many other of thoſe Firebrands of that Rebellion, were men tied by Subſcriptions, and yoaked with theſe Licenſes: yet being men of no Conſciences, theſe nor any other Ties could hold them, but like maſterleſs Swine, broke through the Quickeſt hedges of Laws, and Canons, with theſe Yoaks about their Necks. Which alſo proves <hi>Barrows</hi> Character true of the
<q>Lecturers, That they had Counterfeit ſhews of Holineſs,<note place="margin">Barrow ib.</note> gravity, auſtereneſs of manners, preciſeneſs in trifles: but large Conſciences in matters of greateſt weight.</q> And withall ſhews, that the very Reaſon urged for the neceſſity of Licences, <hi>viz.</hi> to ſtop the Preaching of Sedition; doth rather prove the uſeleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of them to that End; by the very Inſtance given.</p>
            <p>Having cleered the Truth of theſe <hi>Seven</hi> Particulars, and thereby proved the unreaſonableneſs of urging Incumbents to take Licenſes to Preach; There are two Things farther to be ſpoken to. <hi>Firſt,</hi> To inquire in what Caſes Licenſes to Preach may be neceſſary. <hi>Secondly,</hi> To Anſwer the Arguments brought for the taking of Licenſes by Incumbents.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> In what Caſes Licenſes to Preach may be neceſſary. Seeing the true End of Licenſes, is to bring men, admitted to any teaching Office in the Church, to ingage and Subſcribe to Conformity in Doctrine, Worſhip, and Diſcipline, practis'd in the Church of <hi>England:</hi> we judge it Reaſonable, that thoſe on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be required to take ſuch Licenſes, as are not known to have made ſuch Promiſes, Subſcriptions and Ingagements to the Church, at Inſtitution or any other way. Such are</p>
            <p n="1">1 Lecturers, that are not Incumbents in the Dioceſs, where they Preach ſuch Lectures: becauſe the Biſhop may not be aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of ſuch Subſcriptions, Promiſſes, and Ingagements.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Can.</hi> 1603 <hi>can.</hi> 36.</note> This we believe to be the meaning of the 36 Canon, in which the three Articles for Subſcription are contained. The words of which are, <hi>No Perſon ſhall hereafter be received into the Miniſtry:
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:43918:13"/>nor either by Inſtitution, or Collation admitted to any Eccleſiaſtical Living; nor ſuffered to Preach, to Catechize, or to be a Lecturer, or Reader of Divinity— except he be Licenſed, either by the Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop or Biſhop of the Dioceſs (where he is to be placed) under their Hands and Seals: or by one of the two <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities, under their Seal</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Except he ſhall Firſt Subſcribe to theſe three Articles following, in ſuch manner and ſort as we haw here appointed.</hi> From whence we gather, 1 That all Officers in the Church ought to have a Licenſe to their Office. 2 That this Licenſe ought to be under the Hand and Seal, of ſome Archbiſhop or Biſhop of the place, or of the Univerſity. 3. That this Licenſe is in order to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force their Subſcription to the three Articles. 4 That the word <hi>Licenſe</hi> is not determined in its ſignification, for it may be a Licenſe to enter the Miniſtry, or a Licenſe for Inſtitution, or Collation: or a Licenſe to Preach: or to Catechize: or to be a Lecturer or Reader in Divinity. The Firſt we call Letters of Ordination: the Second Letters of Inſtitution. The Third, Fourth, Fifth, and Sixth, are properly Licenſes of Preaching which we inquire after. 5 The Licenſe of either Univerſity can aſſign no place for any man to Preach, except amongſt themſelves: as to the <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Margaret</hi> Profeſſors; and the Proceeding Graduates in Divinity: with the ſetling and diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing them (it ſeems) the Univerſities are intruſted. Any other Licenſe they can give, is but a Commendation of a Profeſſor, for his ability in his Profeſſion: which is to be Reckoned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the beſt ſort of Teſtimonials, in all parts of the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an World: but can give no Authority to preach any where, but amongſt themſelves.</p>
            <p>The Lecturer therefore, by this Canon, is oblidged to take a Licenſe to Preach: and he ſhould be the more carefully lookt after, that the Church run not twice aground on the ſame Quick-ſands. Nor ſhould the Biſhops be over forward to grant ſuch Licenſes, without the Conſent of the Incumbent; ſeeing he hath an Intreſt in the Cure.<note place="margin">Barrow <hi>Ib.</hi>
               </note> And (as <hi>Barrow</hi> obſerves) <hi>their main buſineſs was to alienate the Hearts of the People from the Parochial Miniſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We the rather expound the ſaid Canon, for a Licenſe of Preaching to Lecturers,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Can.</hi> 37.</note> becauſe the very next Canon ſingles out, thoſe that are Licenſed to Preach in the former Canon by the reſtrain'd fence, of <hi>Licenſed to Preach, Read Lecture, or Catechize.</hi> So that we Judge the Licenſe to Preach, only referrs to them, and not to any Incumbent.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:43918:13"/>
            <p n="2">2. Publick ſtipendiary Catechizers, ought alſo to take theſe Licenſes to Preach; as being mentioned in both the Canons, and indeed, Catechizing is one way of Teaching, as Preaching is another. And 'tis meet thoſe men ſhould be Orthodox, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable to the Church, leaſt they ſhould infect young veſſels with ill Sents in Religion. The <hi>Jews</hi> call'd the Catechized <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh</hi> from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Imbuere,</hi> becauſe he receives a Tincture by it, which may be falſe unleſs well looked after.</p>
            <p>'Tis too true we have but few ſuch now,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mart. Tr.</hi> § 2 p. 86.</note> diſtinct from Paro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chial Miniſters; but <hi>Martinius</hi> hath proved <hi>Catechiſtarum praeter Epiſcopos &amp; Paſtores fuit peculiaris Ordo;</hi> and inſtances in <hi>Pantaenus, Clemens, Origen,</hi> &amp;c. in the Church of <hi>Alexandria. Juſtin</hi> Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr was Converted by Catechizing;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Juſt. Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tir Apol.</hi> Cypr. l. 3. <hi>ep.</hi> 22.</note> which he commends much to the Senate of <hi>Rome.</hi> And <hi>Luther</hi> calls himſelf <hi>Diſcipulum Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſmi. Optatus</hi> was a Catechiſt in <hi>Carthage</hi> in S. <hi>Cyprians</hi> time. S. <hi>Mark</hi> is ſaid to turn the great School of <hi>Ptolomey Philadelphus</hi> in <hi>Alexandria,</hi> to a School of Catechiſing. And <hi>Pamphilus</hi> a Chriſtian Philoſopher ordained a famous School in <hi>Caeſarea</hi> for this purpoſe: which had eminent Teachers in them; we have by S. <hi>Pauls</hi> a School <hi>Catechizationis</hi> in <hi>London,</hi> and in the late Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Doctor <hi>Busby,</hi> is ſaid to have ſet up ſuch an Officer in S. <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garets Weſtminſter:</hi> 'tis pitty there were not many more, yet without oblidging themſelves, by Subſcriptions to teach Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodoxly, and conformably to the Faith, and Diſcipline, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed in the Church, they would only ſerve to increaſe Hereſy and Schiſm.</p>
            <p n="3">3. We muſt add to theſe the <hi>Curates,</hi> employ'd under Parſons, and Vicars, to ſupply their Cures, who, ſhould they take no Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe to Preach or ſerve the Cure, would give no Caution to the Church for their good behaviour in it. They would be the only Freemen in it to Preach and practiſe as they Liſt, being obliged to nothing. The Canon reaches them too, in that it orders none ſhall be ſuffered to Preach without being Licenſed. The Church hath as much Reaſon to fear them as any other, becauſe They are commonly young men, hot, and raſh, and may hope by overturning the preſent Eſtabliſhment to be the true Owners, of what they are now but Truſtees. And are apt to Court the People for advantage. And gave ſome inſtances, of their helping hand, in the overthrow of the Church, in the fatal Revolution of the great Rebellion. And if there be any others in the like ſtate, they ought to be obliged, by the ſame methods: for where there is <hi>Eadem Ratio,</hi> there is to be <hi>Idem Jus.</hi> As thoſe that have Donative, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:43918:14"/>
            <p>We are now to proceed, to Anſwer the Arguments brought for Incumbents taking of Licenſes to Preach.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>
               </label> 1. Tho' Ordination give Authority to Preach, yet it aſſigns no place to exerciſe that Function in, nor no People to whom the Ordained may apply that Office; ſo that a Licenſe muſt be taken to appoint out the place, or men would run in heaps to the ſame place, and introduce endleſs Confuſion: in as much as the Prieſts would not know, which of them ought to Preach; nor the People, which of them they were bound to hear.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> 1. We conſent that Ordination aſſigns no place, to exerciſe our Authority in; but It refers the Practice in expreſs words, <hi>To the Congregation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>V.</hi> Office of Ordin. of Prieſts.</note> 
               <hi>where Thou ſhalt be Lawfully appointed thereunto.</hi> Which place the Biſhop knows before hand, for He is not to Ordain without a Title. It being an ancient Rule in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law of this Realm, That no Biſhop may ordain Laymen, to the Order of Clerks, above the number ſuffizing to ſerve the Churches, as that old Author hath it, in the mirror of Juſtice. And the Canons of 1603 ſhewing that <hi>It hath long ſince been pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mir. Juſt. c.</hi> 1. §. 3. <hi>p.</hi> 14.</note> 
               <hi>by many Decrees of ancient Fathers, That none ſhould be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted either Deacon, or Prieſt, who had not firſt ſome certain place, where he might uſe his Function</hi>— They therefore Decree,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Canon</hi> 33.</note> 
               <hi>That henceforth, no Perſon ſhall be admitted into ſacred Orders, except he ſhall at that time, exhibite to the Biſhop, of whom he deſireth Impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of hands, a Preſentation of himſelf, to ſome Eccleſiaſtical Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment then void in that Dioceſs.</hi> &amp;c. Providing that if any Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop admit any that hath no Title there enumerated <hi>He ſhall keep, and maintain him with all things neceſſary, till he do prefer him to ſome Eccleſiaſtical Living.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Inſtitution is the Inſtrument, by which the place of Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and performing all other Functions of an Incumbent, is <hi>Lawfully appointed.</hi> For Licenſes to Preach are unknown to the Law. Inſtitution avoids all Confuſion. And without Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion aſſign the place of Exerciſe, of the Miniſterial Calling, it is altogether uſeleſs.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Licenſes to Preach, may name a Place, but can aſſign none: becauſe it is not the legal Inſtrument to give the Title, nor can we take any Induction upon ſuch Licenſe ſhould it be granted, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ice <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:43918:14"/>gave us power to do theſe, but aſſigned no place, and without a certain place, we ſhould run into Confuſion; one may with as much Reaſon urge a new Grace to every Diſh of Meat, that comes up at a Dinner. The Argument is <hi>fallacia Conſequentis;</hi> It being a plain <hi>non ſequitur,</hi> That Ordination aſſigns no place, therefore we muſt take Licenſes. The true Conſequence is, therefore we ought to have <hi>Inſtitution.</hi> In a word he that holds this Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment good, is at home in no Principles but in Popery. For he muſt believe Preaching to be no eſſential part of a Prieſts office; but that the formal Reaſon of a Prieſt is, to offer Sacrifice, and to Remit Sins, according to the true notion of the Council of <hi>Trent.</hi> But to as many as believe the <hi>Ratio Formalis</hi> of a Prieſt, is Preaching the Goſpel, and celebrating Divine ſervice, and Sacraments: The Argument is a plain Abſurdity. Yet God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid we ſhould think, thoſe that uſe it, took it out of the <hi>Trent</hi> Cloak-bag.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>2</label> The Canons of 1603. do Require that Beneficed Men take Licenſes to Preach: For the 45 Canon mentions <hi>Beneficiati ad Concionandum admiſſi.</hi> And the 46 <hi>Benefeciatus ad Concionandum non admiſſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> 1. Thoſe Canons mention no Licenſe to Preach. 2. Nor is it the deſign of them to Require Incumbents, or any other to take ſuch Licenſes. 3. Only they may ſuppoſe, that the weak Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh converted Incumbents, ſuffer'd to continue in Benefices: or thoſe weak Men the Reformers at firſt put in; might be obliged to take Licenſes before they Preached. 4. The Canons may reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect Benefices, that are not Preſentative, but Donative; of which there are many in <hi>England:</hi> and ſuch Incumbents having no Inſtitution, will need Licenſes both to Preach and do all other duties of a Miniſter in their Benefices. 5. Nor is it likely, any thing hinder'd thoſe Beneficed Men from Preaching, but their own inability, ſeeing the 46 Canon requires and inſtructs, them, to procure others to Preach for them. <hi>Concionem per Corcionato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem legitimè approbatum haberi procurabit,</hi> once every Month at leaſt. For he that appoints whom he pleaſes, may do it himſelf if he could. 6. We doubt not but a Church ought to Examine who is fit to Preach, before he be allowed; but this the Roman Church did not require, in their Maſſing Prieſts: therefore they exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined them not. And 'twas in vain for the Reformers to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine theirs, whom they know to be inſufficient for it: But the Biſhop ever ſince, is bound to examine this Ability before the Ordination, and ſo there is no Room nor Occaſion for Licenſes
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:43918:15"/>to Preach, as diſtinct from Ordination and Inſtitution, in this preſent State of the Church. A Helmet may be uſeful in a Battle, but it ſhew'd <hi>Mark Coleman</hi> mad, to wear one every night in his Bed. 7. In ſhort the deſign of the 45 Canon was to command all men that were able, to Preach one Sermon, in their Cures every <hi>Sunday:</hi> but becauſe ſome could do it, and ſome not, the Canon diſtinguiſhes and Requires only them that were admitted to Preach: and the 46 requires thoſe that could not, to procure one that could: and this is the Summ of the matter.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>
               </label> But it is very Expedient that Incumbents take Licenſes to Preach, to prevent Error in the Church, and Sedition in the State.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> Would Licenſes to Preach work theſe mighty Feats, He were to blame, that would not make them <hi>Annual:</hi> So great a Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit were a cheap Purchaſe at 10 <hi>s. per Annum</hi> a man. But alas! men fancy what brings them profit, is profitable alſo for every Thing. The Mountebanks Pill cures all Diſeaſes. <hi>England</hi> hath labour'd under more Hereſies Schiſms and Seditions, ſince this Antidote was Invented, than ever It did before; as is too evidently Demonſtrated in the 7th Propoſition. If thoſe Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Ties, of Subſcription to the 39 Articles, with a ſolemn Promiſe, in the preſence of God, and in the Face of his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, to Preach no contrary Doctrine, will not reſtrain men from Preaching Errors, how ſhould a meer Licenſe to Preach effect it?</p>
            <p>And he that can Preach againſt or diſuſe the Common Prayer, or inveigh againſt the Diſcipline of the Church, after Subſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the 3 Articles conteined in the 36 Canon, in theſe words I <hi>N. N. do willingly, and ex animo, Subſcribe to theſe</hi> 3 <hi>Articles above mentioned, and to all things that are conteined in them.</hi> There is no hope that any chains but thoſe that are Everlaſting will hold that man. Much leſs can this dull Tool do it, that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies no Tye but Authority to Preach. In truth the Church could find no better Links than what men make with Their own Pen: unleſs they ſhould advance an Inquiſition.</p>
            <p>But we may well wonder, why thoſe Licenſes are no <hi>N</hi> more earneſtly urged than before. Conſidering 1. The General Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty granted by the State to Preach any thing, ſo they im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugne not the Doctrine of the Trinity. 2. And the Practiſe of the ſeveral Sects that Preach what they pleaſe: and will endure no Obligations to Reſtrain them, from God nor Man.
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:43918:15"/>3. And the Practiſe of Latitudinarans in the Church, that can explain the Myſtery of the Trinity into Tritheiſm. And ſhew us that we may worſhip Gods in a greater, and Gods in a leſſer Sence, without believing themſelves oblidged to the Contrary, by theſe Licenſes. 4. And that the proper Legal Subjects of Eccleſiaſtical Power are ſwept away, namely the High Commiſſion for puniſhing Hereſie, and the Star Chamber for puniſhing Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditious Preaching, and Conventicling to diſturb the State. Would they ſhackle the Clergy, while the Sects cuff out their Eyes. 5. After ſuch Recorded Subſcriptions, and ſolemn Promiſes, as Incumbents have made, what need they fear their Preaching Hereſies and Schiſms; unleſs they believe them Knaves! eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſeeing they are the only Banks left to ſtop the Inundation of Errors that threaten to drown'd all before it. 6. Were Men ſincere in their Zeal againſt Errors, one would think the moſt probable way to ſtop them, were, to Intercede with the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to ſhut the Floud-Gates, which they have opened to Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines. 'Tis no ſmall ground of Suſpition, that the ſtopping Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors is not the Thing deſigned: while men pretend to ſtop Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors that are poſſible only, when they attacque not them that are flaming amongſt us. 'Tis certain the Clergy at preſent have no Liberty to doat upon Queſtions; having work enough to ſecure their Pariſhioners Conſciences; from the Infection of ſuch Errors as the Sects broach among them; and to confute their pernicious Pamphlets.</p>
            <p>If the matter aimed at, be a Power to out any Incumbent of his Cure, under Pretence of Preaching Error or Sedition. We may ſay the Biſhops of the Church, have power enough to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prive, for Hereſy and Schiſm, for Diſobedience and Incorri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gibleneſs, as Mr. <hi>Naſh</hi> can tell you in his Caſe. And for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumelious words of the Book of Common Prayer, as Mr. <hi>Robert Cawdry</hi> can ſhew in his Caſe. Mr. <hi>Parkers</hi> Caſe alſo can ſhew that a man may be deprived for Drunkenneſs,<note place="margin">v. <hi>Repert. Can.</hi> c. 27. <hi>Pars. Law.</hi> c. 17, 18. <hi>Pars. Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel.</hi> lib. 1. c. 9.</note> if he refuſe to Reform after Admonition. And in truth (if our Authors de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive us not) any Crime may deprive a Man, if the Crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal ſtand Forty days Contumacious after Excommunication; ſo it be a Crime of Eccleſiaſtical Cognizance: and deprivation be its Puniſhment Canonical: and that the Canon be not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the known Law of <hi>England.</hi> And the Fact be not diſcharged bv ſome general Act of Pardon. But ſtill if the Party ſo deprived will bring his Action for Tythes againſt his
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:43918:16"/>Pariſhioner: the Validity of the Biſhops Sentence will come into Queſtion, and muſt take its Fortune. As it was ſaid in <hi>Burtons</hi> Caſe, where the Parſon was deprived for Adultery, but a general pardon intervening, He was Reſtored, without the Eccleſiaſtical Court,<note place="margin">Hab. ſearle and Will<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iams caſe. f. <hi>293.</hi>
               </note> becauſe the Judgment of Pardons, belong to the Common Law. And ſo it will be, if the Biſhop deprive any, after Revolt from Subſcription and Licenſe according to the direction of the 38 Canon. However if an Occaſion of deprivation be the deſign, the Clergy ought to be the more wary, of admitting ſuch an Innovation, ſeeing it hath ſo ſharp Teeth.</p>
            <p>As to that Part of the Objection that referrs to Preaching <hi>Sedition,</hi> we may ſay 1 Subſcription to the three Articles Secures that too. Seeing the Firſt of the three vindicates the Royal Rights. 2 Oaths of Allegiance are much ſtronger than theſe imagined Ties 3. There are Laws enough to ſuppreſs ſuch Preaching and Puniſh them. 4. Licenſes to Preach, are not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Inſtruments to hinder Preaching in any kind. 5 Many in 1640. did under theſe Licenſes, Preach Sedition: We find there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore upon the whole matter, theſe Licenſes to Preach, are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient for nothing, more than to bring in Fees, which yet, if they muſt be continued, ought to be given <hi>Gratis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>4</label> However Incumbents muſt take Licenſes to Preach, any where but in their own Cures, ſeeing Inſtitution can Authoriſe them no farther, than to their own Pariſhoners.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> We may ſee by this Objection, that cloſe fiſted Avarice, will hold faſt its Prey, whilſt any (tho' never ſo weak) Pretence can be made. But we may knock off its Fingers by ſhewing, that whoever is Ordained a Prieſt, hath power to Preach, in any part of the Catholick Church, wherever He is lawfully called to it. And who can doubt, but a Biſhop may have Lawfull Power to call a Man to Preach at a Viſitation, or to the Lord Mayor of <hi>London;</hi> or before the King; Or any Miniſter to have power to call any to help him in his own Cure. 'Twas never yet denied but an Incumbent's Authority is ſufficient, to inable him to perform by another; what Sickneſs, Neceſſary Abſence, or any other Lawful Impediment, makes him unable to do in his own Perſon. 2. Doth not the 46 Canon Authoriſe, and command him to call in a Preaching Miniſter once a Month at leaſt; If he cannot do it himſelf, Men uſe not to Preach in any Neighbours Church, but at their Requeſt: or
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:43918:16"/>in caſe of vacancy, by a Licenſe to ſerve the Cure. 3. If it be neceſſary to take a Licenſe to Preach in another Pariſh, is it not neceſſary, alſo, to take another Inſtitution, or Licenſe to celebrate Divine Service, or Sacraments there? Or if not, may not the Incumbents Intreaty, be as ſufficient for Preaching as for Celebration of the Service and Sacraments? Any thing but Avarice would bluſh at ſuch trifling Objections. In truth he that Preaches, and he that Officiates, in any other place but his own Cure, doth it not by his own immediat Authority, but by the Right of Him that calls him to his aſſiſtance. But 4 Let it be ſuppoſed that <hi>Titius</hi> hath no Right to Preach any where, but in his own Cure, will the Biſhop grant him a Licenſe to Preach in <hi>Sempronius</hi>'s Cure? will not <hi>Sempronius</hi> think that injury to himſelf? and Uſurpation in the Biſhop? will not ſuch a Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe introduce all the Confuſion complained of? For in many ſo Licenſed, which of them can command the Pulpit? which ought the People to hear, ſeeing all are alike Licenſed to Preach?<note place="margin">Otho. conſt. <hi>t. 12.</hi> cum ſit Ars, <hi>&amp;</hi> Conſt. <hi>13.</hi> ut. <hi>5,</hi>
               </note> would not the Patron alſo think himſelf wronged, by ſuch an Intruſion? yea the Conſtitutions Provincial forbid it, <hi>Exigit namque Ars noſtra Catholica, ut unicus in una Eccleſia ſit Sacerdos,</hi> ſuch alſo is that of <hi>Stephen Langton</hi> in the Council at <hi>Oxford, Anno.</hi> 1222. <hi>Nec de caetero plures vicarij in eadem Eccleſia conſtituantur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Canoniſts indeed ſay The Pope may Preach in all the world: The Biſhop in any place of his Dioceſs, and the Incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent in his own Cure: But none ſay, the Biſhop may Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rize two, or more, in the ſame Cure: which yet muſt be, upon this ſuppoſition. And 'tis very improbable, any man would take a Licenſe to Preach; where he hath no particular Intention to Preach; no more than he would take out a Matrimonial Licenſe to Marry, where he hath no thoughts to Marry.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obj. </seg>5</label> But ſtill 'tis urged; That the Canons imply at leaſt, That In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumbents ought to take Licenſes to Preach: therefore it ought to be done.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> 'Tis true that men have long fancied this, having had the Jaundiſe of Gold upon Them, they thought the Canons looked yellow on them. Hence one while the Chancellors and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſaries challenged the Right, to grant Them: another while the Biſhop damns all Theirs, and advances his own. One while the Licenſes are Parochial, another while Dioceſan, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times Provincial, as the Itch of Lucre moves: but in truth tho' there may be ſome Umbrage, yet there is none that cleerly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands the taking of ſuch Licenſes by Incumbents, and Burdens
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:43918:17"/>cannot be impoſed on the Subjects, by probable Implications, without expreſs words, as the beſt Lawyers generally affirm. The Canons cited to prove the duty of taking ſuch Licenſes, are the 45 and 46. The 45 ſays <hi>all beneficed men allowed to Preach, ſhall Preach one Sermon every Sunday.</hi> Where <hi>allowed to Preach</hi> Is put in, to Excuſe thoſe that were not able to Preach,<note place="margin">Const. Prov. de off Archi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presb.</note> from this Command. For all were allowed to Preach, that were Inſtituted, if they were able, by the Conſtitutions of the Church, <hi>That all Rectors and Vicars ſhall inſtruct the People committed to their Charge Pabulo verbi Dei.</hi> Nor can it be ſuppoſed, That any Inſtituted to a Cure of Souls, was forbidden to Preach, ſeeing that would be <hi>malum in ſe,</hi> and contrary to the Canons, and, deſtructive to the People: but his inability might be wink't at, till able: and then might be allowed <hi>Ore tenus,</hi> by kind incouragment: with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out wax and Parchment. Or ſuppoſe the Beneficed man were upon a Donative, then he ought to take a Licenſe, or would be a Preacher without Subſcriptions. But the Firſt ſeems moſt agreeable, becauſe the 46 Canon requires That a Beneficed man not allow'd to Preach, ſhould procure a Sermon once a Month: which is beſt explain'd by being wink't at or excuſed from Preaching as unable; for elſe he was not only allow'd, bit Requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to Preach <hi>Jure Scripto</hi> by Virtue of his Inſtitution, if Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox and Able.</p>
            <p>The 36th Canon bids faireſt for a Licenſe to Preach, but cannot be ſo underſtood generally. The Words are recited be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore. <hi>No Perſon ſhall be received into the Miniſtery except he be Licenſed;</hi> this muſt referr to a Licenſe of Ordination, called Letters of Orders. <hi>Not admitted by Inſtitution to any Living</hi>— <hi>except he be Licenſed;</hi> this we call Letters of Inſtitution. <hi>Nor Suffered to Preach, to Catechiſe, or to be a Lecturer or Reader of Divinity.</hi> This we call properly a Licenſe to Preach; and ſo that Canon is accounted for Conformable to the Canons and Practiſe of the Church. But the other way ſuppoſes we muſt have a Licenſe to Preach, before we can be ordained, or be brought into the Miniſtery.</p>
            <p>'Tis probable theſe Conſiderations ſwayed that wiſe and Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Man, the preſent Biſhop of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> the true Ornament, and Defender of this Church, to wave preſſing of theſe Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſes, in his Primary Viſitation. And to tell us: <hi>All Perſons who had Cures of Souls and Legal Titles,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Biſh. Of Worceſter. charg. p. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>were ſaid to be Miſſi a jure, ad locum &amp; Populum Curae ſuae; and therefore might Preach to their own People without a ſpecial Licenſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:43918:17"/>
            <p>Upon the whole matter, ariſes this Queſtion: whether thoſe Officers that have Receiv'd Mony for theſe Licenſes, ought not to Refund it.</p>
            <p>To which it may be anſwered, that they ought to make Reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution: becauſe they can have no Conſcionable Right to it. For the Fruits of Impoſture, Extortion, and Coſenage, are accurſed Things. And thoſe that take more than they ought, ſtand ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Conſt. prov.</hi> l. 3. c. 6. <hi>de Inſtit.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ab ingreſſu Eccleſiae, donec haec contra recepta, Solventibus Reſtituantur; &amp; laeſo ſuâ culpâ ſatisfaciant in praemiſſis,</hi> as <hi>John Stratfords</hi> Council determins, in 1342. And in another place, the Council determins, if any Require more than is allowed, <hi>Ingreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum Eccleſiae ſibi noverint interdictum, quouſque de duplo Satisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem, impenderint ſolventibus competentem;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Id. Conc. <hi>l. 3.</hi> tit. <hi>22.</hi> de cenſib. <hi>v.</hi> cap. ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vas.</note> Double Satisfaction the Conſtitutions in moſt places impoſe, upon Extortion of Officers. And ſo 'tis decreed in Extortions, at Viſitations, and Corrections of Incumbents. The Gloſs adds, if the Archdeacon receive Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curations when he doth not viſit, <hi>forſan quia Epiſcopus eodem an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no viſitavit, &amp; ſuſpendebat Iuriſdictionem Archi Diaconi.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Id. ib. cap. Quama is. lex nature.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Now we have ſhewed before, that tho' <hi>Arondell</hi> in his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil at <hi>Oxford, Anno,</hi> 1408. had Decreed, that Licenſes to Preach ſhould be granted, by the <hi>Dioceſan,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ib. in cap. ut ſingula.</note> 
               <hi>ſine aliquali Exacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one pecuniae,</hi> And again <hi>celeriter expediantur &amp; gratis, difficultate quacunque ſemotâ,</hi> without any exaction of Fee, Delay, or Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty; with what Conſcience then can Men retain, what they extort from a poor, but humble Clergy,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Conſt.</hi> l. 5. <hi>tit</hi> 5. c. <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verendiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mae,</hi> &amp;c.</note> almoſt reduced to Extremety, by other inſupportable Burdens. Yea <hi>John Anton</hi> a Canon of <hi>Lincoln,</hi> in his notes ſays: He that grants theſe Licenſes, may take nothing, <hi>Etiam ſi ſic Licentiandus gratis volu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erit aliquid ſolvere:</hi> Tho' Men pay it willingly,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gloſſ.</hi> 16.</note> they can't hold it honeſtly. We will add no more, being perſwaded, that if Mens own Rules, will not convince their Conſciences; no Reaſons will prevail. For we have made it plain from their own Laws, that whether Men ought to take theſe Licenſes, or ought not; yet no Money is to be paid for them: Or if any be paid, that it ought to be Reſtored again.</p>
            <p>If it be urged, that the Officers cannot ſubſiſt, by doing the work <hi>Gratis,</hi> it is already anſwered by the Conſtitutions themſelves.<note place="margin">Conſt. Prov. l. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>22.</hi> c. ſaeva. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> That the Ordinary is bound to provide main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainance for them, if the allowed Fees will not do it: thus <hi>Stratfords</hi> Conſtitution, that aſſigned the Fees, declared, <hi>In cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teris vero Ordinarij ſuis: teneantur Ministris ſtipendia conſtituers,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:43918:18"/>quibus debeant merito contentari: Stephen Langton</hi> in his Council at <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> forbids any thing to be taken for the Paper, or rather Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of Collations,<note place="margin">Canſt. Prov. l. <hi>3. t. 6. c.</hi> quia jux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta.</note> Inſtitutions or Induction; but as the Title hath it, <hi>Collator Gratis conferat, &amp; ſe per ſe, &amp; per ſuos.</hi> The Biſhop is to ſettle any Incumbent or <hi>Praebend Gratis,</hi> farther than what the Canons allowed. And the Queſtion is there put by <hi>Lindwood,</hi> whether the Notary, or Secretary may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive nothing, ſeeing no man is bound to ſerve in War without Pay, and brings in many ſaying, <hi>quod Epiſcopus debet talibus ſcribentibus, de ſuo providere.</hi> And produces another Rule out of the Law. <hi>Quod ſicut Epiſcopus Gratis Epiſcopatum ſuſcepit, it a mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bra ejuſdem Epiſcopatus Gratis diſtribuat,</hi> which anſwers that of our Saviour; <hi>Freely you have Received, Freely Give,</hi> and at length Reſolves, that if any thing be taken for the <hi>Subſtance</hi> of any thing to be done, in Ordination, Collation, Inſtitution, or Induction; It will be Simony: but if it be not of the <hi>Subſtance</hi> of the thing to be done, but mere Writing or the like, they may Recive as much as that labour deſerves, and no more.</p>
            <p>Thus the Caſe ſtood in the Reign of <hi>Hen.</hi> 5. <hi>An.</hi> 1422. when the famous Canoniſt <hi>Linwood</hi> Dr. in Laws, returned from his Embaſſy to <hi>Spain,</hi> and compoſed the Provincial Conſtitutions which have ever ſince been held in great eſteem, by Reaſon of his skill in the Common, and Canon Law of this Kingdom, and accordingly made Dean of the Arches; and after Biſhop of St. <hi>Davids;</hi> And theſe Canons and Conſtitutions, as far as they are not contrariant to the Laws of the Kingdom, nor repugnant to the Royal Prerogative, are eſtabliſhed to be uſed and execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, by an Act made in the 25 <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>chap.</hi> 19. Which Act though it were Repealed by Queen <hi>Mary;</hi> yet was Revived a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, 1 <hi>Eliz.</hi> 1. and ſo they continue to this day.</p>
            <p>To Conclude therefore, it is adviſable, before Men grow ſo eager to vend Licenſes to Preach, to conſider, what our Lord Chriſt will think of ſuch Prieſts, as may Baptize but not Preach: as may Communicate, but not inſtruct their Charge; ſeeing a Prieſt is properly a Miniſter of Chriſt, one of the ſacred Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders: He inſtituted: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the Elders that <hi>Prieſt it well,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim,</hi> 5, 17.</note> are ſuppoſed <hi>to labour in word and Doctrine:</hi> Elſe ſhould they not be called Prieſts, but Sacrificers; as the <hi>French</hi> Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation of the Bible, allways renders the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Miniſters, <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificicatours</hi> and <hi>Sleidan,</hi> and many others, call the Popiſh Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters <hi>Sacrifici.</hi> And that ſuch as Chriſt ſent, were to Teach all Nations, as well as to Baptize them. What God hath joyned to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:43918:18"/>'tis great Confidence in Men to keep aſunder, unleſs there were more to be got by it, than a periſhable Fee. Can theſe two Prieſts, be both of one Order; Chriſt's, that could Teach and Baptize? ours that could Baptize, but not Teach, ſeeing they differ in an Eſſential part of their Calling.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> They ſhould conſider too, what the Primitive Church would think of ſuch Proceedings: ſeeing they never heard of any Licenſe beſides Ordination and Miſſion: nor of any Prieſt but what could and ought to Preach as well as Baptize.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> They ought alſo to conſider, what Neighbour Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es and Nations, will Judge of our Miniſtery; when they ſhall hear that we Ordain, and Inſtitute Prieſts, that have not Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to inſtruct their People.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> They might do well alſo to conſider, what the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Pariſhes of <hi>England,</hi> may deem, the Church Rulers are about to do, in ſending them Miniſters, that have no Power to Preach among them. Will not they be apt to ſuſpect, ſuch Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers have little care of the Peoples Souls. And that they are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to ſettle Sir <hi>Johns</hi> among them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> Nor is it wholly to be ſlighted, what the ſeveral Sects of this Kingdom, may judge of the National Miniſtry; may they not take occaſion from hence to affirm, our Prieſts to be no Miniſters of Chriſt, ſeeing they have not Power to Preach the Goſpel, by their Ordination, and Inſtitution; without ſome farther Authority. We know their Readineſs, to Catch at the ſhadow of an Argument againſt our Miniſtry, to give ſome alleviation to their Schiſmatical Guilt, and to ſupport their ſinking cauſe. But hereby we ſeem to thruſt a Cudgel into their hands to drub us and our Miniſtry withall. It had been far better our own Mouths had been ſhut in this Point, than to Open ſo many Mouths againſt us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſtly,</hi> It may not altogether be unworthy our Conſideration, what our Reformers would think of theſe Licenſes to Preach, now urg'd; ſeeing they changed the very Simbols of Ordination; laying aſide the Chalice and Patin, and inſtead thereof, putting the Teſtament, or Bible, into the hand of the Prieſt, in his Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination: Requiring, and enabling him to take Authority, to Preach the word of God. Thereby evincing that in their Judgment, Preaching was an Eſſential part of the Prieſts Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice; and that it was a fault in the Roman Church needing Reformation: That they made only Maſſing Prieſts, and took
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:43918:19"/>too little Care of the Preaching part. They might ſuſpect by ſuch Licenſes, we would deform the Reformation: and Relapſe into an Opinion, that <hi>Hoc facite</hi> makes a Prieſt: or at leaſt that a Licenſe had been a better Simbol, than their Bible, to be delivered in Ordination.</p>
            <p>You ſee (dear Sir) my Thoughts in this Affair, and ſome of the Reaſons of them. And may peradventure gueſs from hence, that Profit, and; importunity of Officers may blind wel-mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Men. I believe you know my Reſolution, to comply with this our common Mother, in every Indifferent thing. But I fear, if this were well ſifted, it would appear more Dangerous, than the Sticklers for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t are aware of: But I leave the whole to your clear and candid Judgment, to Act according to thoſe Dictates it ſhall perſcribe, Remaining</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours, in our common Saviour. <hi>J. M.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
